hi my name is Joe brewer and I want to
share a story with you several years ago
I set out to study the cognitive and
behavioral sciences with the goal of
trying to understand large-scale human
behavior to address the global
sustainability crisis something that I
learned along the way was that it's very
difficult to get people in key
decision-making positions to recognize
the importance of this problem or to see
that the solution actually exists so
here's my story I was an atmospheric
scientist six years ago when I started
to really dig into the deep systemic
problems that were causing climate
change and global ecological decline I
realized that having another scientist
studying this problem wasn't really
going to solve it that the deeper or
more fundamental issues reside in the
social norms and values that drive
large-scale human behavior and the
incentive structures of our institutions
such as corporations that put the wrong
set of priorities in play such as near
term profits without recognizing
long-term systemic risks and that
actually we have to change human
behavior so I started studying cognitive
sciences by this I mean neuroscience
psychology linguistics anthropology and
a host of related fields to try to
understand how human behavior works and
what we need to do to change the stories
that drive our culture around growth
consumption engagement and a whole host
of other things and what I found was
that this knowledge while incredibly
important and absolutely essential for
solving the deep systemic problems of
sustainability were really difficult to
get recognized prioritized and funded by
advocacy efforts in the sustainability
realm now why is that it turns out that
one of the fundamental issues that we're
grappling with in dealing with
sustainability is a question of what it
means to be human there are a lot of
speculations a lot of assumptions about
what it means to be human they go way
back in our philosophic history and many
of those assumptions it turns out are
not grounded
in truth the not grounded in a
fundamental understanding of how human
beings work and furthermore they're
deeply tied to our sense of identity of
who we are and what it means to be a
good person so for example if you study
cognitive neuroscience which is this
field of research that looks at the
processing of information in the brain
and the exchanges of chemicals through
hormones in the brain that shape our
emotional responses and how we think
about and understand the world you learn
that most of what we consider to be the
underlying drivers of human behavior
happen outside of conscious awareness
and are largely shaped by what are
considered to be non-rational driving
forces so what this means is that the
way we make decisions is not a process
of logical deduction based on facts that
we see in the world but it's more about
implicit beliefs values judgments that
are strongly emotionally driven and
deeply culturally contingent in other
words they're about who we think we are
and what it means to make good decisions
so to go into a room where there are a
set of experts who believe that they
have an understanding of the facts that
they have an understanding of the
problems and the solutions and to convey
to them that those understandings are
not grounded in rational deductive logic
but in fact are shaped by preconceived
notions implicit value judgments and
strong social emotional ties to identity
is a deeply threatening proposition so
one of the major barriers to
understanding and applying insights like
these from the cognitive sciences is
that people in decision-making positions
have to understand that their own ways
of thinking could be biased and could be
inhibiting them for making effective
decisions in other words their sense of
free will and autonomous freedom to make
decisions is fundamentally threatened
and potentially unviable that's a pretty
scary thing to grapple with so it's been
very difficult to get people to
understand the importance of these
insights and to apply them effectively
in creating viable solutions